Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees Miscellaneous Records 5005
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees Miscellaneous Records
1925-1969
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees (BMWE)
5005
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Consists chiefly of working agreements, protective agreements, mediation agreements and legislative materials from the labor organization, Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees.
3834203
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, April 01, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, April 01, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees was organized by workers responsible for the physical condition of operational railway rights of way. It was founded in Alabama in 1887 as the Order of Railroad Trackmen.
In 1892, the Order merged with the Brotherhood of Railway Section Foremen of North America, a related organization, to form the Brotherhood of Railway Track Foremen of America. In 1896, the membership of the union was opened to white track laborers as well as foremen and the organization became known as the Brotherhood of Railway Trackmen of America. In 1918, the Trackmen reintegrated a secessionist faction that had existed as a separate group since 1914 and became known as the United Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees and Railway Shop Laborers. The union adopted its current name in 1925 as part of an effort to settle jurisdictional problems with other American Federation of Labor unions.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1925-1969
Bulk dates: 1962-1969
This collection includes protective agreements covering employees in the event of the merger of the Norfolk and Western Railroad with the Nickel Plate Railroad (1962), the Great Northern, Pacific and Burlington Lines (1968), the Pennsylvania Railroad and the New York Central Railroad (1964); working agreements between Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees and Norfolk and Western Belt Line Railroad (1969), Clinchfield Railroad (1965), Pittsburgh and Shawmut (1967), Toledo Terminal and Railroad Company (1969), and Akron, Canton and Youngstown Railroad (1969). It also includes legislative materials, including the Brotherhood manual for state and provincial legislative representatives (1963), minutes and bylaws of the Ontario Legislative Committee (1966-1969) regarding protection of level crossing, national transportation policy, insurance, election of provincial legislative representatives, compensation cases (McGilliuray Report), and the Workmen's Compensation Act. The records also include the history and bylaws of the Cooperative Legislative Committee (Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, Railroad Trainmen, Railroad and Steamship Clerks, and Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen) and the minutes of the Ohio State Legislative Convention of the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees (1966) regarding elections of state legislative representatives.
Additional materials include a booklet entitled "Milestones of Progress: A Brief History of the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees;" the Washington Job Protection Agreement of 1936; a vacation agreement (1941) between Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers Conference Committees and employees represented by 14 co-operative railroad labor organizations. Additionally there are committee and referee decisions docket 1-146, a union shop agreement (1952); a reference manual on the mediation agreement of 1965 (job security) and other mediation agreements (1964-1965); and an award and interpretation of Arbitration Board No. 298 regarding travel time and away from home expenses.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4004: ILR School Librarian's Office Files /4212: Kheel Center Current Documents Correspondence 5007: U.S. Emergency Board No. 175 Transcripts and Exhibits 5027: U.S. Emergency Board No. 178 Transcripts 5149: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Records 5182: William J. Doble Papers 5347: Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, ICC, and Erie Lackawanna Briefs Regarding the Railroad Merger 5448: Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees Lodge 1179 (Cadosia, NY ) Records 5478 mf: AFL-CIO Railway Employees' Department Records on Microfilm 5484: Railway Labor Executives' Association Records 5488 B: BRAC Records 5488 C: BRAC Additional Records 5489: Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company Agreements 5533: Chicago & Northwestern Transportation Company Records 5583/3: Archives Organization File (AOF) Part 3 5605: Jacob Seidenberg Additional Arbitration Records 5663 mf: Collective Bargaining Agreements on Microfilm 5693: Labor Editorial Files 5728: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5735: BRAC Additional Records 5780/014 P: ILGWU Local 22, Charles S. Zimmerman Photographs 5806: U.S. National Mediation Board Agreements 5897 mf: Strike Files of the U.S. Department of Justice, Pt. 1 on Microfilm 5953: Jacob Seidenberg Additional Arbitration Records 6030: Archival Collective Bargaining Agreements File 6046: Archives Union File (AUF) 6104: Arnold Zack Additional Arbitration Files 6215: Neil P. Speirs Collection of U.S. Railroad Retirement Board Member Files
Labor laws and legislation -- Canada; Labor laws and legislation--United States.; Labor unions -- United States -- Political activity; Railroads -- Employees; Arbitration, Industrial -- Railroads -- United States; Job security -- Railroads -- United States; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- Railroads -- United States; Washington Job Protection Agreement.; Workers' compensation -- Railroads -- United States; American Association for Social Security; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.); Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Brotherhood of Railway, Airline and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employes; Burlington Northern, Inc.; Co-Operative Legislative Committee, Transportation Brotherhoods, State of Ohio; Nickel Plate Railroad; Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen; Pennsylvania Railroad
3834203
- Akron, Canton and Youngstown Railroad Agreement, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Clinchfield Railroad Agreement, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Great Northern Pacific and Burlington Lines Merger Agreement, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Norfolk and Portsmouth Belt Line Railroad Agreement, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Norfolk and Western Agreement, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Pittsburg and Shamut Railroad Agreement, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Pennsylvania and New York Central Railroads Agreement, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Toledo Terminal Railroad Agreement, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Mediation Agreement, Case No. A-5987, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Scope and Contents
  Between Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committees and employees represented by Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees.
- Reference Manual on the Mediation Agreement of February 7, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Vacation Agreement, 1941-1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Washington Job Protection Agreement, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Washington Job Protection Agreement, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Washington Job Protection Agreement (Copy 2), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Rates of Pay. Central Western Region Volume 2, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Award and Interpretations of Arbitration Board No. 298, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Legislative Committees, 1940-1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Manual for State and Provincial Legislative Representatives, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Milestones of Progress, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  A Brief History of the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, Founded 1887
- Railroad Retirement Act and Railroad Unemployment Insurance Act, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Railway Labor Act, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 21)